hi friends today i'm going to teach you
how to crochet a super easy beginner
friendly baby blanket the stitch used in
this pattern is one of my favorite baby
blanket stitches because after
completing the setup row you only have
to remember and repeat one row i love
the simplicity and modern look of this
stitch and i hope you will too
don't forget i have the full pattern
written out for free on the liliness
website which i've linked to in the
description below okay let's get started
before we begin i'll quickly go over the
supplies that you'll need to make your
baby blanket
so you'll need two colors of worsted
weight yarn i chose to work with amigo
xl 100 acrylic worsted weight yarn from
hobby yarn
you'll need a size h8 or 5 millimeter
crochet hook
a yarn needle or tapestry needle
to weave in any loose ends and a pair of
scissors to cut your yarn
now that we've covered the supplies we
can begin working on our foundation
chain
so the foundation chain for this baby
blanket is 120 stitches
i'm just going to show you a smaller
swatch and the multiple for this stitch
is four so you just need to chain a
multiple of four
so i'll chain 24 stitches for just for
demonstration purposes and you can work
along with me with 24 stitches to
practice this stitch or you can chain
the full 120 if you want to work on your
own baby blanket
so i'll begin by making a slip knot and
i'm assuming that you already know how
to make a slip knot how to chain how to
single crochet and how to double crochet
so if you do not know how to do these
things then look them up and come back
to the video
so i've made my slip knot and i've
inserted my hook into the slip knot and
now i'm going to chain 24
chains
so there's my little foundation chain of
24 stitches
okay so we have our foundation chain and
now we can begin crocheting our first
row
for the first row we double crochet in
the fourth chain from the hook
so i like to crochet in the back back
bumps of my of my uh chains not into the
front
because i feel like it leaves a prettier
edge but you can crochet however you've
learned how to crochet into your
foundation chain
so i'm going to count down to my fourth
chain and then work one double crochet
into that chain
one two three four so it's this one
so i work one double crochet into the
fourth chain from the hook
and then skip the next three chains so
this is where the repeat begins so we
count one two three we skip those three
and then we work
a single crochet a chain three
and three double crochets into the next
stitch
i'm working one single crochet
and then i chain three
and then i work three double crochets
all in the same stitch
or chain
this is what it looks like
and then all we do is continue what we
just did so we skip the next three
chains
one two three and then
single crochet
chain three
three double crochet
into the same chain
pretty easy hey so you can already see
how it's starting to look
so i'm just going to continue on
down to the end of the row and show you
how to finish the row when i get there
okay so now i'm at my last four stitches
and i'm ready to work the last steps
so once you reach the last four chains
you want to skip three chains and then
single crochet in the last chain
so i skipped three chains and now i'm
crocheting
single crocheting into my last chain
and then chain three
and turn your work
and that's it for row one
row one was our setup row and now we're
ready to begin row two which is actually
the row that we complete for the rest of
the pattern
so this is the row that you need to
remember
to begin row two we work one double
crochet into our first single crochet so
if you remember from the last row we
ended with a single crochet in the last
stitch
that's the one that we want to work into
so it's this single crochet
so i'm working one double crochet into
my first single crochet
and then we skip the next stitches
and we work
our repeat into the chain three space so
that's this chain three space here
you'll see them throughout the row
that's where we're going to work all of
our stitches until we get to the end
we work one single crochet into our
chain three space
chain three
and then work three double crochets into
that same space
like so
and then we just continue on so we skip
all of the stitches and just work into
our chain three spaces
so again i'm going to do my repeat of
single crochet
chain three
and then three double crochets
so i really enjoy this stitch because it
works up really quick
it's easy to remember and it's just fun
you can this is like one of those
stitches you can work on even while you
watch tv or listen to a podcast
there's not much thinking involved it's
so easy
especially once you get the hang of it
you just you'll just be flying
okay so now i'm at the end of my row
and you can see that i still have my
turning chain left from the last row
so it's really important that you catch
this turning chain and it's it's out
it's obvious here for the first row but
when i show you the next row you might
see how you could get a little bit
confused there
so i'm going to work my last stitch
which is a single crochet
into the last double or into the turning
chain space
like so
and then chain three
and turn your work
and
repeat row two all over again so i'm
going to do one more repeat of row two
till the end so i can show you what i
mean by
accidentally missing that last turning
chain
so i work one double crochet again into
my first single crochet
and then i begin my repeat of working
into my chain spaces
so the first time i did this stitch i
was a little bit confused at the end
what to do
and i actually
missed this last turning chain
the first time and my blanket kept
getting skinnier because i was
forgetting that last spot so
don't do that don't be like me and
crochet your last single crochet into
your last chain or turning chain space
like that
and then your edges will be nice and
straight
so you can see like it looks like you
may have made a mistake here
and it's just the way that this pattern
works it looks like you've started here
but
don't worry when you go back your ends
will be perfectly straight
okay so i'm at the end of a row and i'm
ready to begin my next row with a new
color so to add a new color we finish
off our stitch
our our row with our last single crochet
but instead of finishing our single
crochet we leave our last loop to pull
through with the current yarn color we
drop that color and cut it and then
grab our new yarn color
which is white in this case
and finish off our single crochet with
that new color like so
so i pulled through the last loop with
the new color
so you can see that there's a seamless
transition there and the the colors do
not overlap
and that's what we want
and now i can begin my neck i can begin
chaining three and working my next row
with my new yarn color
so we'll yarn over work our first double
crochet with our new color
and then continue crocheting just as we
had with the old color
so that's what it should look like when
you add your new yarn color
okay so now i'm going to show you how to
finish off your blanket
as you can see the top is bumpy and the
bottom is straight and with a blanket
and most things that we make we want the
top and the bottom edges to lay flat
so i'm going to show you how to finish
off your
blanket with your last row being flat at
the top
so you begin as normal by working your
first double crochet
into that first single crochet and then
you single crochet into your next chain
three space just like before
but this is where where it's different
so we chain three
and then instead of working the uh
double the double crochets into that
chain three space again we just skip
that step
so we single crochet into our next
chain three space
so i'm just chaining three and single
crocheting into my chain three spaces
and then once you reach the end of the
row
there should be two stitches left your
last double crochet and your last
in the single crochet
the first single crochet that you made
in the
last row
so that's that's the single crochet it's
a little bit difficult to see but you
can see you have your three double
crochets and then your chain three and
then that's your single crochet working
backwards
so that's where we we want to work our
next double crochet to finish off the
row and then we work one more double
crochet in our turning chain
and that's it we can fasten off
and weave in our ends
and that's it for this pattern i hope
you enjoyed it if you did please give
the video a thumbs up on youtube and
subscribe to my channel
you